I could never understand. My misfit suddenly had a fit, and for a while, I got giddy with a newfound confidence I had in my thinking. But after Grandma died, that confidence took a dive, because thinking is how I grieve. And in that grief of thought, I could suddenly see with so much clarity just how profoundly isolated I was and always had been. What was the purpose of my human? I began to think a lot about how autism and PTSD have so much in common. And I started to worry, because I had both. Could I ever untangle them? I'd always been told that the way out of trauma was through a cohesive narrative. I had a cohesive narrative, but I was still at the mercy of my traumas. They're all part of my soup, but the onions still stung. And at that point, I realized that I'd been telling my stories for laughs. I'd been trimming away the darkness, cutting away the pain and holding on to my trauma for the comfort of my audience. I was connecting other people through laughs, yet I remained profoundly disconnected. What was the purpose of my human? I did not have an answer, but I had an idea. I had an idea to tell my truth, all of it, not to share laughs but to share the literal, visceral pain of my trauma. And I thought the best way to do that would be through a comedy show. And that is what I did. I wrote a comedy show that did not respect the punchline, that line where comedians are expected and trusted to pull their punches and turn them into tickles. I did not stop. I punched through that line into the metaphorical guts of my audience. I did not want to make them laugh. I wanted to take their breath away, to shock them, so they could listen to my story and hold my pain as individuals, not as a mindless, laughing mob. And that's what I did, and I called that show "Nanette." Now, many -- (Applause) Now, many have argued that "Nanette" is not a comedy show. And while I can agree "Nanette" is definitely not a comedy show, those people are still wrong -- (Laughter) because they have framed their argument as a way of saying I failed to do comedy. I did not fail to do comedy. I took everything I knew about comedy -- all the tricks, the tools, the know-how -- I took all that, and with it, I broke comedy. You cannot break comedy with comedy if you fail at comedy. Flaccid be thy hammer. (Laughter) (Applause) That was not my point. The point was not simply to break comedy. The point was to break comedy so I could rebuild it and reshape it, reform it into something that could better hold everything I needed to share, and that is what I meant when I said I quit comedy. Now, it's probably at this point where you're going, "Yeah, cool, but what are the three ideas, exactly? It's a bit vague." I'm glad I pretended you asked. (Laughter) Now, I'm sure there's quite a few of you who have already identified three ideas. A smart crowd, by all accounts, so I wouldn't be surprised at all. But you might be surprised to find out that I don't have three ideas. I told you I had three ideas, and that was a lie. That was pure misdirection -- I'm very funny. What I've done instead is I've taken whole handfuls of my ideas as seeds, and I've scattered them all throughout my talk. And why did I do that? Well, apart from shits and giggles, it comes down to something my grandma always used to say. "It's not the garden, it's the gardening that counts." And "Nanette" taught me the truth to that truism. I fully expected by breaking the contract of comedy and telling my story in all its truth and pain that that would push me further into the margins of both life and art. I expected that, and I was willing to pay that cost in order to tell my truth. But that is not what happened. The world did not push me away. It pulled me closer. Through an act of disconnection, I found connection. And it took me a long time to understand that what is at the heart of that contradiction is also at the heart of the contradiction as to why I can be so good at something I am so bad at. You see, in the real world, I struggle to talk to people because my neurodiversity makes it difficult for me to think, listen, speak and process new information all at the same time. But onstage, I don't have to think. I prepare my thinks well in advance. I don't have to listen. That is your job. (Laughter) And I don't really have to talk, because, strictly speaking, I'm reciting. So all that is left is for me to do my best to make a genuine connection with my audience. And if the experience of "Nanette" taught me anything, it's that connection depends not just on me. You play a part. "Nanette" may have begun in me, but she now lives and grows in a whole world of other minds, minds I do not share. But I trust I am connected. And in that, she is so much bigger than me, just like the purpose of being human is so much bigger than all of us. Make of that what you will. Thank you, and hello. (Applause)
que nunca lograba entender. Mi incompatibilidad de repente era compatible. y por un tiempo, estuve mareada con esta nueva confianza en mi manera de pensar. Pero después de que mi abuela falleció, esa confianza se desplomó, porque mi forma de hacer el duelo es mediante el pensamiento. Y en ese dolor de pensamiento, pude entender claramente lo profundamente aislada que estaba y que siempre estuve. ¿Cuál era el propósito de mi humanidad? Comencé a pensar mucho sobre como el autismo y el TEPT tenían tanto en común. Y empecé a preocuparme, porque tenía ambos. ¿Podría desenredarlos alguna vez? Siempre me dijeron que salir de un trauma se hacía a través de una narrativa cohesiva. Yo tenía una narrativa cohesiva, pero seguía a merced de mis traumas. Todo era parte de mi sopa, pero las cebollas seguían apestando. Y en ese punto, me di cuenta de que contaba mis historias para hacer reír. Había recortado la oscuridad, quitando el dolor y aferrándome a mi trauma para la comodidad de mi audiencia. Estaba conectando otras personas mediante el humor, mientras yo quedaba profundamente desconectada. ¿Cuál era el propósito de mi humanidad? No tenía una respuesta, pero sí tenía una idea. Tuve la idea de contar mi verdad, toda mi verdad, no para compartir risas, sino para compartir el dolor literal, visceral de mi trauma. Y pensé que lo mejor sería hacerlo a través de un espectáculo de comedia. Y eso fue lo que hice. Escribí un espectáculo de comedia que no respetaba el remate, esa remate donde se espera que los humoristas saquen sus golpes y los conviertan en cosquillas. No paré. Atravesé de un golpe ese remate directo al estómago metafórico de mi audiencia. No los quería hacer reír. Les quería quitar el aliento, dejarlos en shock, para que pudiesen escuchar mi historia y sentir mi dolor como individuos, no como una muchedumbre inconsciente y que ríe. Y eso hice, y llamé a ese espectáculo «Nanette». Ahora bien, muchos... (Aplausos) Muchos argumentan que «Nanette» no es un espectáculo de comedia. Y pese a que estoy de acuerdo con que «Nanette» no es un espectáculo de comedia, esa gente aún está equivocada (Risas) porque han enmarcado su argumento para decir que he fallado en hacer comedia. No fallé en hacer comedia. Tomé todo lo que sabía sobre comedia todos los trucos, las herramientas, el conocimiento, lo tomé todo, y con ello, rompí la comedia. No se puede romper la comedia con comedia si fallas en hacer comedia. Flácido sea tu martillo. (Risas) (Aplausos) Ese no era mi propósito. Mi propósito no era simplemente romper la comedia. Mi propósito era romper la comedia para poder reconstruirla y reformarla, reformarla en algo que pudiese sostener mejor todo lo que necesitaba compartir, y eso es a lo que me refería cuando dije que dejé la comedia. Probablemente llegados a este punto dirán, «Sí, genial, pero ¿cuáles son las tres ideas exactamente? Es un poco impreciso». Me alegra haber hecho de cuenta que preguntaron. (Risas) Estoy segura de que algunos ya han identificado las tres ideas. Son una multitud inteligente, según dicen, por lo que no estaría nada sorprendida. Pero estarían sorprendidos de descubrir que no tengo tres ideas. Les dije que tenía tres ideas, y eso fue una mentira. Fue pura desorientación... Soy muy divertida. Lo que he hecho en su lugar es coger a manos llenas mis ideas como semillas, y las he esparcido a través de mi charla. ¿Y por qué hice eso? Bueno, aparte de risitas, se reduce a algo que mi abuela solía decir. "No es el jardín, es la jardinería lo que cuenta". Y «Nanette» me enseñó la verdad de esa perogrullada. Esperé que al romper el contrato de la comedia contando mi historia con toda su verdad y dolor que eso me empujaría más lejos en los márgenes de la vida y el arte. Esperaba eso, y estaba dispuesta a pagar el costo para contar mi verdad. Pero eso no fue lo que pasó. El mundo no me alejó, me acercó. Mediante un acto de desconexión, encontré conexión. Y me llevó mucho tiempo entender que en el centro de esa contradicción está también en el corazón de la contradicción de porqué puedo ser tan buena en algo que soy tan mala. Verán, en el mundo real, me es difícil hablar con personas porque mi neurodiversidad me dificulta pensar, escuchar, hablar y procesar nueva información todo a la vez. Pero en el escenario, no tengo que pensar. Preparo mis pensamientos por adelantado. No tengo que escuchar. Ese es su trabajo. (Risas) Y no tengo que hablar realmente, porque, estrictamente hablando, estoy recitando. Entonces todo lo que queda es que yo lo haga lo mejor que pueda en crear una conexión auténtica con mi audiencia. Y si algo me ha enseñado la experiencia de "Nanette", es que la conexión depende no solo de mí. Uds. juegan una parte. "Nanette" puede haber empezado en mí, pero ella ahora vive y crece en un mundo entero en otras mentes, mentes que no comparto. Pero con las que confío estar conectada. Y en eso, ella es mucho más grande que yo, como el propósito de ser humano es mucho más grande que todos nosotros. Hagan de eso lo que quieran. Gracias, y hola. (Aplausos)